the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
all right welcome everyone to the stowa
i'm peter limberg the steward of the
stoa and the stowe is a place for us to
go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
nice edge of this very
moment and for those of you who may be
new
here to the store or watching for the
first time
what is estoa no one really knows some
people call it a communal podcast a
digital campfire
a wisdom gym and it's probably better
not to know
one thing we do have here is a
sensemaker in residence
series this is a four-part series over
a month where a sense maker comes in and
tries to make sense of the world
with us and today uh for the month of um
october on mondays we are very lucky to
have
uh our friend daniel schmuckenberger
visiting us
and this series is called the digital
porch and the idea here is
we're coming in with no theme or agenda
we're just going to sit on the digital
porch with daniel
and ask questions uh and this was
daniel's idea
because the original stoa uh the
original name of the stowe was estoyly
which meant the painted porch which is
where the stoics uh got their name uh
they just hung around the with xeno on
the painted porch
philosophizing with each other so that's
what we're going to do today
and um i will take daniel in in a moment
and then
and we'll jump into the protocols as
well but
if you were here the last time daniel
was was here we
ended the session with flowing through
annoyingness
sessions so every monday one of our
facilitators tyson wegner
has um purposes freestyle wrap with
sensemaking
and it's on a different link usually but
we just kept it on this link
and for this month tyson is going to
experiment with something different
called
rap unbattles uh rap battles
you know use kind of rap to tear people
down but rap unbattles is using um kind
of this the same technique to
bring people up so i'm to take in tyson
in a moment to just
um just kind of introduce this
tyson are you with us right now if
you're going to meet yourself
yeah i'm here thanks peter yeah after
party
following the digital porch come hang
out kick it we're going to
battle rap stoa style and the best part
is
even if you've never rapped before you
can still play so
look forward to seeing you there cool
thanks tyson and so that's going to be
on the same link uh
after this session which is about 75 to
90 minutes i will take a bio break and
then tyson will be tagged in and you can
you can leave or stay and watch and or
whatever you like um
so in a moment i'm going to take daniel
in and the protocols of today is if you
have a question
anytime uh during um the session just
write it in the chat box
um have like a cue or question
beforehand i'll call on you unmute
yourself
ask a question to daniel if you want me
to read on your behalf because this will
go on youtube eventually just indicate
that in the chat somehow
and then i'll read on your behalf i
think that's everything
uh so that being said uh daniel
uh welcome back
good to be here thank you peter it's
funny i'm seeing a few faces
that i saw like an hour ago we just did
a live q a with rebel wisdom so
good to see some of you again they're
jumping digital campfires
um is there anything i'll start with the
opening question but is there anything
you want to kind of set the frame for
this series or
for today
i think something that happened in the
last stoa session when it opened
to questions um and someone was
describing
anxiety attacks and i was sharing things
that have been useful for me around that
and
various personal topics is uh
that's really fun it's actually really
fun to get to
address philosophy and
practices that could be useful at a
cultural and civilizational scale in the
context of just what's actually alive
for people
and real questions real dialogue rather
than just in the theory
uh place and with specific topics so
most of the time if i'm
on a podcast it is to share some
topical body of content and so uh the
idea
of making a space to have no topic and
just address what's alive for people
sounded uh fun and worthwhile and like
it would probably end up surfacing
conversations that don't happen
elsewhere
so i'm looking forward to seeing what
happens
awesome um and i sent a google uh
um doc for taking notes i didn't know
who's going to take notes but someone's
jumping in and taking a lead on that
which is awesome
and so the idea here is we're going to
have um each session we'll take notes so
we can have a body of knowledge that we
can uh work with
um so the first question that i have and
someone
basically asked it to in the chats um
maybe if you um feel up for it to
describe the consilience project
again because i know you introduced it
publicly at rebel wisdom recently under
their war of sense making
and you and i have been chatting uh
about it for a last little while
and someone had a question um related to
the stoa
uh how can a place a digital campfire
like this though help with this project
so maybe like a one-on-one on the
project and how can we help with it
i think i won't explain the concept
project from scratch since there
are a couple videos that do that and
someone can just check it out and i
don't
want to take a bunch of time covering
that since i think
many people heard it but the consensus
project
overall is seeking to facilitate a
development in culture
where people have increasing
value around both their own better sense
making of the world
and their ability to sense make other
people's perspective experience and
sense making and communicate effectively
so that we might be better able to do
coordinated problem solving for the big
problems that we care about that we're
not doing a very good job with currently
and uh making sense of
what's really going on with climate
change and environmental issues whatever
is
hard by itself like the complexity of
those is tricky
but then to also make sense of how
that's connected to geopolitical issues
and market issues and other things based
where
one strategy that benefits a part of it
could harm something else
and different sub-populations are
focused on different parts of the
overall landscape that they care about
more
that requires pretty deep sense-making
of not just
complex issues but how lots of complex
issues are interconnected
and how lots of other people are making
sense of it valuing it how they're going
to respond to get a sense of how do we
actually move forward together
and if everything that we do elicits a
counter response that is trying to
counter the things that we do
and there's a kind of arms race of
escalation of
effective counter responses the
coordination cost is too high to really
solve any
of our major problems and we are
actually driving
arms race in conflict in the process
so a cultural value around both better
and more holistic and integrated sense
making and better communication so we
can coordinate particularly with people
that see things differently
than we do because we have to because we
inhabit the planet we just because we
disagree with them and call them stupid
doesn't mean they stop existing and stop
doing stuff
um that's kind of the cultural set of
values
and stoicism as like one of the
uh schools of greek philosophy
had a lot to do with how do we
increase our self-awareness and our
emotional
resilience so that we are not as easily
hijacked by
group think and narrative warfare and
emotional reactivity
that we can actually reflect on our
values and our sense-making and make
good choices from that place
and so if you take that as one of the
you know one of those schools that was
co-occurring with more
of the kind of aristotelian pythagorean
type schools of can we can we get logic
better can we get science and
empirical observation better and with
the kind of socratic dialogue type
school
can we have better quality conversation
and understand each other better
if i can understand myself understand
others understand base reality
communicate effectively across those the
whole population can do that
we have a much better chance of engaging
in something like collective problem
solving or governance
so considering this project has certain
things that we're going to do directly
in terms of types of education and
content
that we put out to try to help make
sense of current world events and teach
people how to do that
but it's also seeking to facilitate the
cultural movement
towards these goals
writ large which means every project
that is trying to make
better digital tools for helping people
search data sets and make sense of
things or better news projects or better
public education projects or better
trauma processing
projects we want to be able to help kind
of recognize all of those as part of a
shared
movement to upgrade culture and
to facilitate those together so i think
the stoa
has the ability to be a place where
practice can occur
somebody can learn an epistemic tool and
then say okay well what does this
actually look like how do i generate a
landscape of all of the narratives on a
particular topic how do we steal man
those are we doing a good job with it
how do we then move from steel manning a
narrative to trying to actually
empirically verify and falsify
individual propositions so
all of the aspects of epistemics and
conversation that one is learning they
need a place to practice
awesome um so we're having
tons of questions and they're all gonna
probably come at you from different
angles so
i'm um looking at them so
rob you're up next
okay it's a long one bear with me um in
my industry there's a pattern common in
many industries where the key decision
makers have a great deal of capital and
influence
while the employees and contractors seem
to have a lot more understanding of the
systemic needs and pressures
that we face and we
we end up losing the game of influence
those of us who feel more informed
even though we have the relevant info
and plenty of will and i think that
matches
the pattern that i see across many
industries
so the question is for those who are low
in the hierarchical stack
what can we do to be more effective in
making systemic change when
the owners of capital have other ends
yeah that's a great pretty perennial
social organization question uh
there's a lot of different answers right
unions historically have been an
answer let's be able to get those people
into some unionized force that has
symmetry
with um capital ownership
democracy has been an answer so forming
a union in the private sector is one
answer
forming a public sector where we say
let's make a government of foreign by
the people that actually has a monopoly
of force even bigger
than the top of the private sector
capital ownership that can enforce rule
of law that's another answer but of
course
capital will end up capturing the
regulatory body
if the people are not fully educated
informed and engaged and actively being
the regulatory body and
most nobody here probably is engaged in
government
all that often as a citizen so it's not
of for and by the people governance it
is a
permanent political class largely
captured by an economic
class and people that have other [ __ ] to
do and then complain about bad
government but are consenting to be
governed by rulers by not being actively
engaged in their own self-determination
um so there's a lot of different kinds
of answers right so
politics would be one answer unionizing
would be another answer
getting better at the game of power
inside of the private sector is another
answer
so figure out how to ladder climb more
effectively so that you can
influence things by being in the c-suite
or in the board or
do a better job at capital accumulation
so that you can influence things as a
shareholder or whatever
what i would say is true across all of
those
another would be create public education
to change consumer demands
right so that the customers are actually
demanding something different so supply
has to create something different
because there's a change in demand
so those are all classic answers right
but what i would say that they all have
in common
and other ones that we could give is
that in addition to the intelligence one
might have about the topic there is a
strategic
intelligence that also has to be there
the strategic intelligence is
doing like what we're doing right now
what are the different ways
to be able to influence what are ways
that i could do
what are ways that i could move into
increasing influence
that wouldn't corrupt the thing that
we're doing and in this given situation
of the various pathways which ones
actually make no sense and are most
actualizable by the people
asking it and so what i would say is if
you want to
be more influential because you believe
that you have sense making that should
be more coupled to choice making
then you actually have to increase the
kind of intelligence not just
sense-making intelligence but the kind
of intelligence
of how influence itself works
could you expand on that last point just
a bit more
when i say how influence works you could
say how power works
which is also synonymous with how
strategy works
right which is what i'm saying by
strategic intelligence so
okay if the if there's a game of power
meaning that
rooted in things like private property
ownership is
a uh
my ability as a person or a family or a
corporation or a nation to advance my
balance sheet independent of or even at
the expense of others of the commons
and there is all kinds of evolutionary
advantage
to get more capital accumulation and
have that capital in service of
generating more capital
and there's scarcity of resource and as
a result of scarcity of resource driving
value there's a basis to artificial
artificially manufacture more scarcity
if i happen to be doing well at that
right
as you as you understand those types of
dynamics the underlying conflict theory
then you say okay
those who get those who figure out how
say we started a market t equals zero
everyone has the exact same amount of
resource and position
people won't be equally good at the
thing right some people
um partly because of luck but partly
because of orientation and aptitude and
capacity
will start to get more resources in the
system and as soon as they have more
resources
they have more capacity to generate more
resources they can employ more people
they can do more to affect the mindsets
of other people through media they can
influence government
through lobbying more they can apply
they can contract private intelligence
they can make sure their kids get the
best education
whatever right so if someone gets more
resource
they both have the incentive and
capacity to protect that asymmetry of
resource and grow it
so then you end up getting a power law
distribution and wealth and that ends up
being an inexorable thing
power law distribution so then you say
okay well if i'm not at the top of the
power law distribution what do i
what do i do if i want to influence this
we'll either have to figure out how to
get up there
that's a certain kind of strategic
insight how does that work
what what what are the ways to actually
do that
or i have to say so there's a power law
distribution in economic wealth what are
the other things that could affect that
well
if i'm down here i don't have cemetery
of power up here so i don't have real
influence
but if i got all of us together so
that's say all of us as workers which is
a union or all of us
as consumers which could create an
influence on supply side so can i do
consumer education
or all of us forming a government that
could then bind this with rule of law
um or can i build a technology
that increases my power through leverage
right so these are basically strategic
insights
around how do i how does the game of
power work
and in the presence of that being the
thing that is determining what happens
largely if i have a sense
that there are better things that could
happen how do i
also develop the capability
to see what the pathways to have
any influence are now how one studies
that
so that i mean you can study military
theory
which is a very good thing to study you
can study game theory and study
coordination there you can study
psychology you can study the biographies
of self-made successful
people you can study
types of asymmetric technology
for the most part anyone who gets good
at the game of power also gets captured
by
it and
so in a way those
who are who seem like they have the most
freedom in agency are also the most
bound
to keep doing the kinds of things that
they have to do to maintain that
position
so like it's you can
critique a world leading critique putin
all you want
for different things but you're like in
the presence of the pressures that nato
and the us were giving and the economic
interests to be able to
take as much of the wealth out of the
ussr as possible and whatever could he
have really done something all that
different
right in the presence of ubiquitous game
theory you either get good enough to
protect your people and do your thing or
you don't and you end up losing to
someone else who's doing that
and so you can see that the people who
seem like they have the most power are
also
the most obligated to behave in certain
ways
given that position
and for the most part those who are
pursuing power are doing it because of
psychological dispositions to pursue
power
and then that's getting conditioned in
the process
and so then if there are people who are
psychologically not disposed to try to
get power
and they're more disposed to care about
the whole but they have no ability to
influence anything
and those who influence it have
given up really caring for the whole and
or become completely
bound by the nature of the system that's
that thing drives extinction right that
separation
of um virtue wisdom
goodness and power those things have to
be recoupled
and
and that means that anyone who has been
pursuing
virtue and wisdom and goodness well who
feels like they have some
insights into how to make better systems
also has to learn
how to increasingly gain the capacity to
be effective
in the current world system without
becoming captured by it or in service to
it
anjon you had a question that would be
good to take on that
hey daniel um it's a related question um
how can you actually get better at games
of power while still remaining game b
committed
i'm thinking that power corrupts or you
get caught up in the game or
just when i pay this mortgage off or
i'll just do this for two more years et
cetera et cetera
i mean being kind-hearted you're also
often at a disadvantage
versus those who don't give a [ __ ]
trying to see who is speaking is there a
video on
it's not coming to the first page he had
his video off
maybe that's why ah
okay i heard most of it um
can you put video on and just say one
more part of it
so i can connect to vr
andren are you are you there still or
um i don't have video right now okay
okay
how do you study the game of power
without getting captured by it is the
question
how do you get effective at it without
getting captured by it yep
uh partly
you have
you have to know what is actually sacred
to you
that you actually have loyalty and
devotion to
beyond utilitarian success in the game
of power
so you know what choices you don't take
and what you're actually taking in
service to
um
and to the extent that someone actually
has a
real embodied knowing of what is sacred
to them that is worth more than
their own personal advancement or life
and their life is in service to that
to the extent that that's embodied and
real and congruent
is the extent to which they can be safe
vessels for power
then there's continuous blind spot
monitoring
and noticing
okay where is
uh some unfulfilled childhood
recognition need
actually coming up and affecting what i
think is the
most useful thing to do in service to
what i care about that is really just
recognition or actual com
competitive ecodynamics or mate
signaling or whatever it is
so there's the need for like there has
to be an extremely
high value on what you actually value
and a value on integrity and
impeccability
to motivate you to have enough
self-inquiry to be looking at and
adjusting those things
oftentimes like it was easier when
someone believed in a
all-seeing punishing and rewarding god
because then there's a motive to be
impeccable because
not one jot not one tittle shall go
unjudged before the day of judgment
right and so
but if i don't believe in a judging god
then why not get away with this thing
that i could get away with
if i'm the only one who knows and
so then there's a question of do i
actually have a sense of what is
meaningful
beyond just what is that personally
advantageous
that is deep enough that i have a basis
for self-respect
that requires integrity that makes me
require integrity of myself
uh the deeper that process is
the more someone can be a safe vessel
for power
and then trusted people around you that
can check you
most people who get into positions of
power get surrounded by yes men who all
want something from them
and as a result continue to say the
things that double down on the bias that
brought the person there
um if you are earnest in your desire
to wield influence for
actual collective good then you should
know that
there are blind spots in yourself you
can't see and there is
collective intelligence that exceeds
your own intelligence about what is
right and so you should be actively
seeking that collective intelligence
about the situation
and actively seeking it about your own
self now that doesn't you have to be
very careful of
who do you trust who they are as people
and they're knowing of you
enough that you're really seeking to
share enough with them that they can
give you that reflection but that's
important
that's the compliment daniel
how does how does one not be handicapped
by having a game b commitment in playing
games of power the example that comes to
mind is
elon musk just firing somebody
turning around and not even thinking
about it twice but somebody with a
kinder heart
something like that being much harder
you can do the hard thing
if it's the right thing
right if kinder heart
makes you
so sensitive to that person that you
aren't
going to make a choice that would be
better for lots of people in the whole
then the kindness is actually myopic
if you on the other side rationalize
this is the right choice for the whole
and so you don't feel any empathy for
that person and you don't take any
considerations around it
then you also become deadened and
there's a dangerousness in that
so i wanted to
i want to care about the experience of
that person and if i have to let them go
i want to feel that but i also don't
want my feeling that to make me myopic
and not make the choice that is in
service of the greater good
uh i have a follow-up that you can swat
away
and it has to do with your personal
relationship with power
um especially when you've you're you're
gaining
increase of influence and your voice is
is getting heard
um is there any moments in your life
where you felt like you were in a wrong
relationship with power
and what did you do to correct that and
maybe what kind of ecology of practices
or relationships you have in order to
keep you in right relationship with
power
i grew up nearly maximally blind
to power dynamics
and that was partly because of being
homeschooled with no kids around like
even just the nature of school
school yard stuff and clicks and bowling
and whatever i just i didn't get
and because of the great fortune of
having
like reading a lot and as a kid but
being exposed to good things so i was um
reading the works of a lot of the great
philosophers that those were actually
the people i was being exposed to and
that's how i thought people were
um and
it was very strange because there was
this there was this kind of
cognitive dissonance that i didn't learn
until later where because then i got
involved in activism and i saw factory
farms and i
just instantly wanted to kill all the
people that
would do anything like a factory farm i
saw the the yulin dog meat festival and
i just wanted to remove that part of the
world
um but
so i knew or study
uh how creative we've gotten with
torture methods
so i knew that there was gruesome abuse
of power in the world
but i was on the outside of it looking
at it
and the few people that i was relating
with were also on the outside of it
looking at it so then i had this kind of
default
that whenever i was talking to someone i
assumed they weren't part of it and
hadn't been conditioned by it because we
were only ever talking about solving
world problems because the only thing i
like talking about
because they were interested in that i
assumed that we were kind of looking at
this thing together
so i ended up trusting people i
shouldn't have trusted
and then having projects be harmed as a
result of that because i was
seeing the highest in people and wanting
to be redemptive all of the time
and um and creating an environment where
the only the highest values and the more
what were being talked about because the
nature of the conversation
and then i also had people assuming i
was playing games of power
who were more power literate because
they couldn't believe that i was as
educated as i was about say sciences and
i was as stupid as i was
about the game of power and i just i
just had a very uneven development that
way
and so then they would say you're just
naivete signaling right now
assuming that i actually knew the game
of power and i was signaling being naive
to it as a method of playing the game of
power effectively
um and i was just like what the [ __ ] are
you talking about i don't know
it was very it was disheartening and
frustrating and so then i'm like okay i
have to understand this so
then it was finally time to read
machiavelli and
um robert green and all like that and
and even then there was still an
outsideness where i'm like
okay so i understand those dynamics but
anybody who i'm talking to about those
dynamics is uh and so it's been a
progressive process
for me i also had this thing where
it made so much sense and i'm so
grateful for it and yet it also
seems so naive and silly to me now
when i when i was a kid and for kind of
most of my growing up i never
asked what do i want to do with my life
i asked what does the world need and
what should humanity do from kind of
this
omniscient perspective right and that
was very useful because i
i thought i couldn't figure out what i
should do if i don't have a sense of
what humanity needs
like i'm embedded in this thing i'm a
part of it so i need to figure that out
first
but that meant that i i wasn't thinking
in terms of my own agency of what i
could affect
so i was i had was thinking about the
sense-making of what would make it
better
decoupled from the how do we get there
that was both extremely useful and
extremely naive
and so then had to get into the okay so
the enactment problem we can't just do
this and that perfect world system comes
about even if we get some people to
agree how do we deal with the fact that
the other
people who don't agree to the non-uh
nuclear
proliferation agreement and who build
all the nukes end up in running the
world how how do we deal with those
types of issues
and then there was like a begrudging
acceptance of
that the path from if you will game a to
game b
requires capacity in both
it is neither game a nor is it game b
game a for game a sake is to win at the
game of power
for the purpose of the game of power
game b to be
played in full requires that being the
game or the context and it's not yet
so that how do we move from where we are
to there requires being
able to not be beat by game a right
which means
understanding it while actually not
seeking to serve its aims but seeking to
change the nature of the game itself and
um
so that that that's a little part of um
kind of my
history with it and then uh
finding people who i think understand
topics better than i do
and seeking their input and particularly
finding people understand topics better
than i do
who disagree with each other and trying
to
understand their perspectives more and
also
where they agree and where they disagree
and why
uh across topics this has always been
something super important to me
and very helpful and then also
i think i used to err in the side of
seeking people's feedback
for my own growth too much because
it was because i knew that anybody's
feedback about me has some value even if
it's largely their own trigger
there's still the question of why didn't
i have the attunement to know that would
be triggering to them how could i have
communicated more effectively to them
right there's going to be signal in it
even if what they're saying is not
objectively true
and that's assuming that they're
communicating in good faith
which i came to recognize is not a fair
thing to assume all the time
and it takes a lot of time because
there's a lot of people
and it's not all equally valuable so
then starting to say okay
i'm going to be more selective in the
people who
uh not who agree with me but who i
respect
both their good faith and earnestness
and their perspective
and be seeking their input
yeah it's an awesome heuristic i'm going
to sneak in a follow-up question
so something that we're looking forward
to doing at the store eventually to
develop courses
and one that you know i think is as neat
as having a power literacy
uh course and as i mentioned to you
robert greene the laws of power is
coming to the store soon
uh where he's agreed to come on at least
um
and you mentioned like studying game
theory the great great people who've
achieved power is there any one single
source that you know of
that has the most bang for your buck
when it comes to uh understanding power
probably robert green okay i mean
what he did in the 33 strategies of war
and the 48 laws
was take a lot of the classics of
military
theory or political theory and break
them into fairly simple principles and
then stories that illustrate the
principles and doing it across cultures
and doing it in a popular way where you
don't have to
really understand um
what this particular period and prussian
history was about to get the cultural
context of why they were writing that
way or whatever
as far as an intro i think those are
probably the best intros
the thing i've noticed about them is
most of the people who i have seen read
them
48 laws in particular
uh get damaged by them
because it you know there isn't
something like a game a game b
context there there isn't something like
the problem
of rivalrous games driving arms races
causing
eventual self-termination it's just
looking at history of what won and let's
understand the thing that wins
and even in the introduction there's
this concept of
um the only thing that wins is the game
of power and
so if you have any ethics or virtue at
all you better get good at the game of
power
because otherwise you won't be effective
which is not all that different than
something i just said
but there's this subtle thing where it
can actually
someone can interpret that in a way that
rationalizes sociopathy
and utilitarianism in general can
make you rationalize sociopathy hey i'm
doing this for this good reason so i
don't feel bad about the thing that i'm
harming
one of the problems with utilitarianism
is my
modeling of the future to say if i don't
do this this will happen
usually is more i'm assuming more
certainty than is actually warranted
and it's on the basis of that false
excessive
certainty that i rationalize the harm
that i cause
if we don't do this thing then china
will do this thing well
there's like 20 steps of unknown stuff
in there
but assuming that thing to be certain
and true
then i do a one-step certain harm
causing now
and this is tricky this is where virtue
ethics are needed to kind of
um offset utilitarian ethics you have to
be doing both you have to be thinking
about the process
and the results and the recursion
between them
there was a question that was bubbling
up in me uh wanting to inquire about
your thoughts on power relating to evil
um
but maybe i'll put that on pause and
throw another question too and maybe you
can decide which one resonates more
uh up in the chat someone was mentioning
about um
what was it again uh sexual selection
how that question
uh uh was sort of dodged on the eric
weinstein's
uh podcaster appearance that the person
who said it was evaded i haven't
listened to that one
and then the previous stoa session you
said you might address it at a different
still
appearance which is related to power
sexual selection dynamics
um so i'll throw that out for you the
question
um so the question is uh do you uh
so i'll read what the person said daniel
evaded answering question on sexual
selection on both eric's
and previous stoa sessions how does
sexual selection impact game a
game b
so i can give you my sense of what a
answer is which is very different than
what
the most ethical game a answers are
meaning that
different axiom sets are going to have
us answer that differently
so from an evolutionary bio perspective
evolution is the result of mutation
survival and mating
right some mutations end up being more
successful at surviving and mating they
go through
and then you get recombinatorial
dynamics in the mating of the
ones that were able to survive and mate
and that that process
and so there's obviously a strong
impulse to survive and a strong impulse
to
mate and a strong impulse to mate with
whatever else looks like
is also evolutionarily maximal mating
opportunity
and so a lot of people take conflict
theory down to this level
and say
either the malthusian thing on survival
humans reproduce geometrically
resources reproduce arithmetically
eventually there will be more people
than there are resources than scarcity
of resource for survival of drives
inexorable competition over over the
not everyone can attain the same stuff
that's kind of a survival selection
answer and it's it's wrong by the way
though
uh it makes all the sense in the world
why malthus said it
at the time but when he said humans
reproduce geometrically
that was before the inflection curves in
population that really started to happen
where populations were going down
without exogenous pressures
and we can see in the nordic countries
and in japan and in wealthier places the
population curves have stabilized and
even went down without exogenous
pressures
and it was also before us getting the
ability to create a closed-loop material
economy and recycle stuff
and upcycle stuff so we don't end up
needing
more resource that is only reproducing
arithmetically forever
we can upcycle it so that
that insight um needs amended
and then when it comes to mate selection
it's a similar thing like
if i assume monogamy is the social
contra
construct um and specifically for
mating and that everyone has a
biological imperative to move their own
genes forward
more than caring about somebody else's
genes or society as a whole or whatever
else
then there will be a place at which you
and i both
want the same mate we both can't have
her it's
a fundament she's a rivalrous good in
that way and
i either beat you or you beat me to be
able to have that mating opportunity
um
now of course uh not all societies have
been rigorously
monogamous we can look at polyandrus or
polygamous or promiscuous societies and
see
that there were different ways of
relating to this all of which still had
some
conflict theory and game theory there
was different ways of solving it
one of the things that what one of the
arguments as to why monogamy was more
selected for and there's many arguments
here and i think it's a
deep topic but one of the positive
arguments brett makes
brett weinstein is
it was a way to ensure that all the men
got to mate
and so they had to when they were young
kind of posture
do whatever peacocking they needed to
land a mate but then once they had it
you had some social convention where all
the guys got to have a sexual and
procreative opportunity and then they
weren't gonna have
more and as a result if i knew you
weren't gonna
gonna try to mate with my wife then we
could coordinate together where if i
didn't know that you weren't going to
try that
then i have to always stay in
competition with you
and if there's a bunch of men who aren't
getting their mating needs met they'll
just break the civilization because it's
not meeting their needs so how do we
make it to where all the men have their
base need met and then stop competing
with each other because they kind of got
the thing they need
now of course that is an idealized
version that pretends that adultery
wasn't ubiquitous
um and you know etc but uh
my game b answer is
that the sexual impulse i mean and this
is true even in monogamy
in monogamy there's the recognition that
you will have sexual impulse towards
people other than the person you're
married to that you're going to witness
and not act on
right so there is this recognition that
you don't act on every impulse
and that there are some choices that
lead to
a healthy life in a healthy society and
there are other impulses that don't that
you have the capacity to have some
volitional
override on i would say that we can just
extend
that um but it's that same
kind of principle and of course in
polyamory there's a similar extension
i can witness my jealousy impulse
and not be controlled by it in the same
way i can witness my promiscuity impulse
and not be controlled by it
can i gain increasing sovereignty over
my being hijacked by sexual desire
and being hijacked by rivalrous desire
or any of those things can i gain the
ability to witness all of them and not
be automatically controlled
so that my virtues and values can
actually be the basis of my choice
making
and i would say whether we're in a
monogamous a polyamorous
a mixed whatever kind of set of social
constructs
the basis of it is that is
that and
and i think here's the core argument and
this is why i actually
there's a limit to evolutionary
psychology that
i end up being unhappy with
the answers it generates all the time is
we have capacities that were not
evolutionarily selected for directly
but are the exceptions of what was
selected for
right so nature selected for
the capacity for recursive abstraction
because it led to tool building and
coordination for hunting but
now that recursive abstraction gives us
the ability to do things that were not
part of our evolutionary selective
environment but we have the capacity so
it's not
default that they will be deployed that
way but it's possible for us to deploy
them that way
and if we if we look in
the rest of nature other than humans on
this biosphere
we are we are really not like anything
else
in the amount of impact that we're able
to have
on all of the ecosystems that we're in
and the nature and the speed the speed
coupling in particular
so mostly we don't compare ourselves to
viruses or mycelium we compare ourselves
to apex predators
and i think people here have heard me
talk about this before apex predator
theory is not a good model for humans
because orcas can't leave
the ocean and go hunt on land and polar
bears can't go hunting the savannah we
were able to become the apex predator in
every environment
so rather than hunt to a certain level
and then have our population checked
they also didn't start factory farms
they also didn't do species extinction
at scale
because and i mean i've used this
example so many times but an orc is
going to catch
one seal or one fish at a time and it's
going to miss a lot of times
and then you look at a drift net a mile
long drift net that pulls up
a hundred thousand fish at once and
you're like that's not apex predator
right like that dwarfs and orca's impact
on fish populations
so much that it's incomparable so if we
keep
modeling ourselves as apex predators and
needing to up regulate
our apexness relative to the other
people so we have to deploy
our exponential technologies of
domination and
whatever to compete with each other
we do destroy we both drive arms races
where the direct conflict is bigger than
the playing field can handle and where
the externality is bigger than the
playing field can handle
so the thing i would say is that our
choice making capacities because of
abstraction and technology
are evolutionarily unprecedented no
other animals
can impact the world in the way we can
as a result of that our evolutionary or
our choice making basis has to also be
evolutionarily unprecedented
and it can be um
and so our capacity to witness
evolutionary impulses in ourselves and
neither automatically be controlled by
them nor
shame them just witness them understand
them and then have a choice-making basis
that is more the result of
um reflection abstraction
values consideration is key to that
question
um so feel free to swat this one away
and i'm being playfully
nosey today um but when it comes to the
the monogamy
poly kind of distinction
how do you relate to that what was your
sort of pathway
and your choice
i have been happily monogamous
i've been happily polyamorous i've been
happily celibate it was important for me
to explore
be with nobody be with one person be
with more than one person
so that i had first person experience of
it i had
knowledge of it and that it was actually
a choice
because if i couldn't do some of them
then it wasn't really a choice it was a
default if
my jealousy was so intense that um
my partner being with someone else would
really freak me out make me lose my [ __ ]
then
and then when i say i'm choosing
monogamy because of this that and the
other value that's really the rational
backfill
to i just can't handle something else um
or similarly if i couldn't choose
monogamy because i'm super afraid of
being trapped and afraid of commitments
and can't control lust processes and
whatever then i
say i'm choosing the other one and it's
a default so it was important to me to
have experience
in
that i can navigate i could navigate
different models right
i could navigate different cultural
models but
who am i as a being and showing up to
relationships with other people is
deeper than the models
and does my okayness
come from a specific model does it come
from the agreement that this person will
never behave in these ways and if they
do i'm totally [ __ ] up or that i
definitely
you know get the opportunity to behave
with these people in these ways or does
it come from a deeper
place than that and
so i can't like
at this point
i can't really imagine being bothered by
who someone chose to have sex with
like that's just not gonna bother me i
also can't imagine feeling like i need
to have sex with somebody in particular
um and so
those are just not things that control
me
and that means that there is not a
obligation to
a particular model of i need to get my
needs met
i think coming to relationships from the
point of view and this is kind of like
common
u.s california um
personal development language of like
needs meeting
i think it it can actually go in a
pretty bad direction
which is hey i have these needs we're in
relationship i need you to meet my needs
is actually just psycho babble for
codependency
and because i need you to meet my needs
means
i can't be not [ __ ] up unless i
control your behavior
i need you to behave a particular way
for me to be okay no you don't
you were fine before you ever met that
person if that person died you'd grieve
and
something else would occur if that
person
was doing that thing that you really
hate but you just moved your attention
to something else and got distracted
you'd be fine
it's the but as soon as i say i need
this person to do that thing i'm
conditionalizing my happiness and then
i'm making that true
for myself now of course i might have
boundaries of
i know the kinds of things i'm
interested in and if someone doesn't
want to do the kinds of things i'm
interested in it just doesn't make
sense for us to do this thing together
like i'm i'm interested in relationships
where we're honest and if
someone else is not interested in
honesty or not capable of it
i'm just not going to choose to do a
deep relationship with them
but i'm not saying i need you to be
honest with me
no i don't i can just interact with you
differently
so i think the coming to a relationship
from a place of sovereignty and
wholeness
not from a place of seeking to get your
needs met in it is a critical part of
navigating
monogamy serial monogamy polyamory any
of those well
um so people are cheering me on to keep
asking you questions so i'll just ask
one more um in let's say you said you're
happily monogamous happy
uh happily polly happily celibate what
virtues did you learn
with each of those what virtues emerged
yeah it's a great question i think there
are times where
i think there are things that can be
learned in celibacy
differently i won't say they're the only
way to learn it
but they can be learned differently than
through other
life experiences i think
they're all of the kind of tantric
practices
of notice sexual energy arise
and see if you can learn how to move it
see if you can learn how to direct that
in a different way
and direct it in
to creativity and to other things
there's really interesting stuff one has
to do when they don't just go to
immediate release
of a very strong evolutionary energy
there's also something around when you
meditate and your nose itches and you
don't scratch it
you just witness it which says i am not
controlled by every biologic impulse
that arises i don't have to scratch it
like
i'll be fine if it just itches and i
watch it there's something around
if i can watch a very strong sexual
impulse and not have to scratch the itch
i become more trustworthy
including more trustworthy to myself
there's also a place of being able to
have a lot more attention with yourself
that can make you both more reflective
and more noticing and integrating shadow
elements
and all kinds of things like that
when you don't put a huge amount of your
attention on other people
and when you aren't seeking to get
fulfillment from other people right away
but seeking to
notice your where unfulfillment arises
inside of you
and inquire more into it and work with
that there's a lot of wholeness and
sovereignty that can be developed that
way
and specifically if someone is coming
from codependence
sometimes that phase is necessary
it's actually necessary before getting
to interdependence to go through a phase
of deep independence that involves even
things like sexual sovereignty
um monogamy
uh in forests one of his landry is one
of his books there's a
line that i think is just beautifully
expressed that
the line is uh for every freedom
multiple
new limits arise and for every limit
multiple new freedoms arise
and this is the recognition that freedom
and limitation
are words that can't be defined without
each other
or a synonym of them they're co-defining
concepts but they're also co-defining
realities
and so the idea the desire for just
more freedom is fundamentally a kind of
immaturity
as opposed to that every freedom has
limitations that come with it costs and
investments that come with it
and i have to embrace them together and
so i'm actually not choosing
more freedom in an absolute sense i'm
choosing the freedoms that are more
meaningful
to me
so
monogamy is a very nice structure to be
able to give up
some things give up some freedoms
and feel good about it and not indulge
feeling resentful or lacking or bad
about it
as an as a choice not because i have to
because of something that i am choosing
because of a freedom i want so maybe
i want to be able to go to places of
depth and commitment psychologically
sexually emotionally with her where i
have to create a safe enough container
for that for that to be possible
that's a freedom there's a freedom that
we can explore certain things in that
container that might not be possible
outside of it
and there are certain limitations i'm
fully willing to embrace
for that um
in open relationship there's this idea
hey that's common of
rather than try to get all of your needs
met from one person which makes you kind
of resent them
and manipulate them to be someone they
aren't you try to force your husband to
dance and he sucks at dancing but he's
good at other things but you're
disappointed in him because he's not
that thing and you like it or whatever
how about just get different needs met
from different people and love each
person for who they are
it sounds like a nice idea and there's
some niceness to it
but there is in the monogamous dynamic
of course to some degree we just get
different social needs met from
different people that we don't have to
be having sex with it's
called friends and community and family
that you can have intellectual and
relational experiences with but there's
also a place of being like hey
i want to grow with you where the things
that are really meaningful to you i want
to grow into and develop to some
capacity
even if i wasn't interested in it on my
own in that topic or that thing because
i'm interested in you and i'm interested
in the connection we have
and there's really um yeah there's
something very beautiful about that
and around saying
where we could diversify our attention
into other relationships we want to keep
deepening it
and let's see how deep can we go into
the depths of knowing each other and
knowing ourselves
through the way we know each other so
there's these are all things that
monogamy can do very beautifully
and there's more and open relationship
and each of these also have a shadow
right
there is coming to celibacy because of
just shame around sex and bodies
or because of just sucking
interpersonally
and not wanting to keep feeling rejected
um or you know other things like that
just being wounded in a relationship and
just retreating into the wound
um there's pathological versions of
monogamy that are really about
control and jealousy and insecurity and
trying to get your security met through
a very secure structure whatever
there's pathological open relationship
that more has to do
with immaturities around more freedom
and of fear of commitment intimacy
whatever
i think some of the things that can be
learned in open relationship well
is different people bring out different
aspects of us
and the more intimate a relationship is
which doesn't have to be sexual but
obviously that
brings a whole depth of intimacy we've
we might find that there
are like it's a common thing i hear
people in open relationship
who are doing it thoughtfully say is
wow i went places in my experience with
you that i've never went with anyone
else but
that's true for everyone there with
because it's just the universe is a big
place
experience is a big place and that the
different chemistries of those people
coming together make different kinds of
like unlock
different things the way they trigger
each other the way they facilitate each
other the way they muse each other
so that's one thing the other thing is
the ability to be very connected to
someone really not ambivalent about
them and also not try to control them
is a very deep process it says i love
you
i want to be connected i'm not
ambivalent about you and i ultimately
want for you all the things you want for
yourself that are good for you
and even if some of that takes you away
from me i want that more than i want to
try to control something that is not
what you most want
that's a very deep and profound and
beautiful process
of moving more into something that i
think deserves to be called love
than control and insecurity
um also getting to
work past rivalry and getting to have a
sense of like
okay i'm doing this prayer about my
desire for the well-being of all mankind
and
holding all humanity as brothers but
really if you [ __ ] with my woman i'm
gonna hit you in the face
i'm just holding you as a rival and my
prayers don't really mean anything right
like
so then there's a question of like what
does it mean to say i want for everybody
and i want to
embrace people's brothers and i want to
have non-rival risks dynamics like
there's a very deep
way and like the the more
intimate the thing that's being shared
is
the more
depth of intimacy in that relationship
and the more overcoming rivalry and kind
of interactions have to occur
so i think all of those structures can
be
explored in a mature way
valuably i think they can all be
described in a mature way for actual
shadow reasons in a kind of pre-trans
fallacy and that's what i see more often
than not
i think open relationship is harder just
fundamentally harder than monogamy
because monogamy
if you notice in our when i say
our culture i'm giving a stat about the
us but i
i think um much of the modern developed
world is similar
when you look at the divorce rate and
the infidelity rate and the people who
are neither divorced nor
in infidelity but who are together
sexlessly or miserably um it's pretty
[ __ ] high across those three right
and you look at how many long-term
marriages are there that are really
fulfilling and beautiful it's like okay
people suck at that just with one person
and it's because relationship is
actually a hard thing
it's i have to like pay attention to my
triggers and my feelings and my wants
and my worldview and my desires
and somebody else's at the same time and
neither compromise what i really need
for what they want which will just make
me resentful
know or push for what i want in a way
that will end up making them resentful i
have to actually
i have to be able to hold more than
myself but including myself
simultaneously
right and i would say everything that's
hard in politics this is a microcosm of
and then of course a family with kids
now we got to do that for more people
we got to be able to be tuned in to and
aware of this whole field of interacting
people
um i would say that
most people can't even deal with
their own needs and feelings and wants
and desires and thoughts
without um driving themselves crazy most
of the time let alone trying to do two
people at once
so uh multiple relationships are taking
what most people are already barely only
succeeding at
and trying to say now let's do multiple
of those at once plus it's a second
order equation because of the
interaction of all of those
so um i
i have not seen people do really well at
open relationship
who didn't do really well at monogamy
um i've seen people who claim they do
and under the hood it's actually pretty
[ __ ] up
um but doing well at monogamy involves
like being able to be really committed
to someone and problem solve and work
through difficult things and an open
relationship is actually being
really committed to more than one person
and being really committed to
someone and the other people that
they're with right as part of an
ecosystem
that's just if someone chooses to do
that they're also going to choose to
invest a lot of development effort in it
yeah that was super awesome um so i'm
gonna stop hogging you
and then pass it to the question to
someone else uh just wanna be sensitive
to the time
uh we're past the hour mark uh are you
okay to go to
uh 20 more minutes
uh sure yeah okay um
hannah you had a question
okay so originally i was going to ask
about
um systemic trauma and your strategy
surrounding that
but what is more likely to me right now
is you know there are some people
like us at the stoa who are interested
in developing
sovereignty and there are some people
for whom that is not a concern
and we work with these people and we're
friends with these people and we're in
relationships with these people
so what what are your strategies
for continuing to develop sovereignty
in relationship to and in connection to
this ecology of people who are not doing
that
so there's a few ways to answer this
so one way is you think about
when someone uh
is transplanting a small tree they plant
a tree in a place
they put tree stakes around it because
it hasn't yet established its root base
maybe they put a fence around it to
protect it from deer or whatever it is
once it establishes its root base you
might be able to
you know tie things to it and use it as
a stabilizer
but to begin with it needs stabilized
in people's personal development it's
that way for most people
where there is a desire to be able to be
stable in a particular set of capacities
or virtues or values to be able to help
other people with it
but there's also the honest
developmental recognition when that's
not true yet
and doing that will just pull the little
tree over
and that the developmentally right thing
is to be around people further ahead
than you
in that particular line of development
until it becomes stabilized enough that
you can
not be thrown off going into places and
that are further off and you can
actually help that's
something i think is an important
consideration so
the i'll say a little bit more about
this because i think it's more important
than
most people acknowledge the
so jewish saying proximity is destiny
that who you are around is going to end
up determining the course of your life
more than any other
single thing is and it's true because as
social primates
we're influenced by what we take in on
tv and by our own thinking and by our
disciplines but we're more
and and the physical environment we're
in but we're more influenced by the
people we're around than pretty much
anything else
and
so being cognizant of that and that's
why there's aphorisms like
um keep the company of the wise and keep
the company of saints and whatever in
every culture that has some wisdom to be
like that's an important thing
and then of course who are all the
people seeking the company of the wise
who aren't there there's obviously a
developmental recognition that people
get to a place where that can be more of
an offering
um
so i would not try to help
people ground in something you are not
grounded in
that's the first thing
the next thing is when you're talking
about your own desire to
increase sovereignty and then that other
people don't have that desire as much
maintaining your own sovereignty with
respect to the where they are
if you get if you get bent out of shape
because they're not
something else um that that's
the place for your practice not for
trying to change them
um your ability to
see them where they're at accept them
except you're
where you're at right and have some
piece around that is
going to be important and then
after those two i would say learning how
to be
more effective at influence is actually
important
sometimes that's paying attention to who
you actually can influence
and sometimes it's paying attention to
what effective influence strategies are
but the foundation of effective
influence strategies with regard to
things like virtue development always
start with your own embodiment and
practice
any follow-up hannah
no i'm good thank you all right
um jason you had a question
hey yeah um so can you hear me
great um so most of the time when i hear
the term collective intelligence it's
coming from
the mouths of intellectuals who are a
tiny fraction of society so
i'm wondering how can we foster a
collective intelligence that's inclusive
and integrates
other forms of wisdom beyond just
education or
kind of like whether it's
self initiated or institutional
is there are there other paths that that
can kind of bring us all
up to speed without becoming an
intellectual
it's an interesting question
there's several sub questions in there
that i hear
um one is does everyone have to develop
their
intellect for society to function well
and refining that would be how much
development of intellect is necessary
to engage as a citizen well
and the other question is what types of
human development other than intellect
are
meaningful and can contribute to
collective capacity in some way
and then how do we engage those
effectively
and maybe also a question around does
everyone
even have similar aptitude
for all of the different kinds of
intelligence and how do we um
work with that and
like those are all very interesting
questions
um
the term collective intelligence is
a term that is not exactly synonymous
but close to synonymous with other terms
that other groups use to mean more
broad things like productive capacity
right there is some relationship between
those topics so
for the most part traditional economists
aren't going to talk about collective
intelligence but they will talk about a
society's productive capacity
and its productive base and they will
recognize that the
invisible hand of the market is an
emergent collective intelligence that is
contributed by
all of the supply and demand and
innovation patterns across the
interaction of all those people
so collective intelligence theory would
look
at the market as a collective
intelligence mechanism
and that what people want
and the up regulation of who supplies
that well and that driving innovation
and whatever that whole kind of market
theory you can look at that through the
lens of collective intelligence and
acknowledge that people's
innovation their creativity their
desires all kinds of things are
part of that other than just their
intellect
there's obviously study and collective
intelligence of types of
group problem solving and coherence and
choice making that are other than
intellectual
like a tribe that gets together and they
have a big decision to make
so they all start by
dancing in a drum circle around a fire
and that doesn't seem like an
intellectual thing but what's happening
is
the drum circle itself is having the
people do their own thing on the
drum but also find synchrony with each
other so there is a
balancing of individuation and harmony
right of sovereignty and
communion and the people who are dancing
are all doing their own dance but all to
the same base beat
so similarly there is a embodied
experience of being an individual in
harmony with other individuals
and that embodied experience where then
they're seeing each other and seeing
their eyes and having that experience
then they sit
and they have a felt sense of their own
individual place
and their connectivity with each other
that changes the state they're in when
they go in to solve that problem
so that's kind of like a social
technology that's a pretty awesome
social technology that evolution
selected for for a long time
that isn't what you would consider an
intellectual process
but absolutely might increase the
quality of problem solving of that group
might it might even make their
intellectual capacities more capable
coming to bear
we can look at other things that it
probably does like move people from a
more sympathetic to parasympathetic
place which makes executive function
more capable and limbic hijack less
possible and you know other things like
that
so the question of are there lots of
different
types of knowing and intelligence that
are possible and
important and can we figure out ways of
engaging all of them and not over
norming on some of them
is a super important question and well
beyond the scope of me answering how we
do that
um
will everyone be equally intellectual
of course not
just like will everyone be equally
artistic or
kind of course not is there a minimum
level
of kindness and a minimum level of
rationality that is necessary for people
to be able to be part of
effective social constructs yes
and this is kind of the baseline of what
we would call a culture
or uh yeah
if you think about the chakras
as a model for types of intelligence
which is a good way to think about them
that each one of them was like a
a center of capacity or intelligence or
wisdom or awakening or something like
that
um the
chakra corresponding to
the solar plexus would traditionally be
interpreted
as being associated with will
that the kind of intelligence that is
is related to what we were talking about
earlier with like power literacy
is there's a the generator question
there is how do i relate
to this topic or this situation in a way
that empowers me
that's a kind of intelligence right it's
a kind of intelligence to say what do i
focus on what meaning do i give it how
do i relate with it that empowers me
which is a different question than what
is objectively true and provable
it's a different kind of intelligence
the chakra that we would associate with
the throat having to do with
communication
if i'm communicating i'm not just
talking at somebody
i'm trying to create communion with them
i'm trying to find
commonality um there's some purpose why
we're talking so i'm wanting what i'm
saying to be
received and land right so i have to
actually put myself to
communicate effectively i have to put
myself in the other person's shoes and
say
how would i communicate this thing to
them where this would land
and wouldn't hit their triggers or be
rejected so
how do i communicate effectively
involves empathy for the other
and self-reflection around what is true
for you and what your intent in
communicating is
those types of intelligence
would be associated with that chakra
and so the intellect
which is the capacity to discern what is
same and what is different
right what do what where is their
sameness or commonality between things
where is their difference or distinction
and then what is the kind of relatedness
you can think of intellect which is
distinct from
what we might call mind mind might
involve
a lot of narratives running and a lot of
identity and software but intellect is
kind of
just the pure compute function of the
capacity for discernment
discerning
truth from falseness sameness from
difference those types of things
and that was actually in in the
yogic chakra system that was the very
highest of the chakras before union with
everything
um what i would say is that any of the
develop like the human developmental
philosophic traditions
i interpret that the highest thing
they're
offering is how to develop all of the
parts of self for everybody
so we can say oh the you know the
heart chakra the the path there is
bhakti yoga
about love and devotion or if it's
uh and maybe the intellect would be gyan
yoga and there are different paths and i
can pick one
i think the more kind of well-rounded
interpretation
is for us to connect with
all the dimensions of our self and
develop all the dimensions of our self
so that there gets to be a maximum
wholeness of self
in the fullest relationship of the
wholeness of reality
so if any for someone to say oh i'm an
intellectual i don't need to feel
their intellect is going to be limited
by the depth of the experience of what
those symbols mean related to the ground
of experience
right um so
i i want a culture where
everyone values intellect and experience
and artistry and awe and all of those
things and everyone
values developing all of those aspects
in themselves in a way that is aligned
and unique to who they are
not that everyone will be developing
them identically or equally
beautiful thank you
awesome um so uh we have about five
minutes left so
let's uh end here um
if uh there's any juicy questions in the
chat maybe you can throw that google doc
we have running so we can kind of save
it for next time
or anything that came alive before i
close out i'll hand it to daniel for any
kind of
concluding thoughts this is kind of a
interesting ride that we went down with
these questions but
anything uh a live view at the moment
oh just this is this is fun it's fun to
have
a group of people that care about these
things and want to take time
to think and reflect and develop
themselves and
and create a community of shared
development both for themselves and in
thinking about
society and civilization more broadly
and the relationship between those of
how do i become a citizen of the future
i want to see how do i develop myself so
that i
can actually apprehend that world and
i'm a part of it
um and so that i'm more capable of
helping bring it about
um that kind of bi-directional
relationship super important
and
uh you know when you um
offered for me to come and do the four
times in a row
i happened to be in a in a very busy
time with trying to launch this project
and so i was thinking okay maybe we'll
do that in a couple years
but um it doesn't actually take that
much time
since it's just questions and you're
hosting it doing all the work of it and
um
and what i think i think this community
is actually very well set to
help the kind of movement process
consilience project is working on asking
these questions being in practice around
it
and uh so yeah this is fun and
i think the intent or the hope was that
these four get to build on each other so
we don't
need to ask the same questions again
mostly we'll kind of
ask new ones and maybe get to reference
earlier things we talked about so
be interesting to see where we get by
the end of it beautiful
um so i'll make some closing
announcements in a moment but uh daniel
my friend thank you for coming to the
stoa
uh during this busy time in your life
and uh if you need the stoa in the store
village to help you with the concealing
project just let us know
and hopefully uh some of the the
questions that you're wrestling with
will get asked here
um so i'll make some closing
announcements for upcoming events
we got one tomorrow with michael taft
from the
uh was it the deconstructing yourself
podcast
that's um 12 p.m eastern time and then
uh
the most interesting man at the stoa
nicholas benjamin has an event called
concept unfolding
uh nicholas could you unmute yourself
and uh tell us what that's about
i think you're still here i'm still here
everybody
so join me tomorrow for part two of
concept unfolding
where i expand on my methodology
for creating concepts and pushing the
limits of our language
beautiful and that's at 6 00 p.m eastern
time
uh and then uh tyson i'll just take you
in again just to kind of if anyone
missed it what's happening on the same
link uh after after this rap on battles
all right yes right here in the same
room is rap unbattles
so it'll be an opportunity to practice
dialect and
good faith dialogue with one another
some healthy argumentation
in a musical way so join me even if
you've never rapped before this is an
opportunity for you to play
and uh have a good time so i hope to see
you there
beautiful thank you tyson so i'm gonna
have to bounce in a moment but i'll hand
over the host access to tyson
uh if you would like to see up more
events we've got tons of events coming
up
um oh i'm so excited to announce this
one uh keith johnstone the author of
inpro uh he's like the founder pioneer
of
the improv movement he's coming to the
stoa i'm super excited for that uh
contra points the famous youtube
personality she's coming on
got a book that um so a lot of events
coming up and go to the start at ca
check out our patreon account and then
our sub stack the mailing list uh
so that being said um i'll play some
music go on a bio break and then tyson
will take over in a moment so again
daniel everyone thank you for coming out
today
you